Guide to the Petra Barth photographs, 2006-2017; 2006-ongoing RL.10024
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Petra Barth photographs
2006-2020; 2006-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barth, Petra
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
RL.10024
14.0 Linear Feet 11 boxes 421 prints
65.12 Gigabytes 728 digital files
Collection consists of 421 black-and-white prints in darkroom and inkjet formats, 726 associated digital image and project files, and two digital videos by photographer Petra Barth. Arranged by project, Barth's images document cultures, politics, environments, and crises in countries all over the world, through landscape and portraiture. Series include images from Central and South American countries to the Caribbean countries of Haiti and the Bahamas; portraits of migrants and images of migrant services at Arizona/Mexico border stations; images from the Chernobyl Exclusion Zone and residents in nearby areas in the Ukraine; scenes in Jerusalem and the West Bank; images of Syrian refugees and others in Jordan camps; and portraits of military veterans of the Bosnia-Herzegovina War. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Born in Bavaria, Germany in 1964, Petra Barth initially studied design in Milan and worked for many years in the fashion industry. In 1999, fulfilling a lifelong ambition, she became a full-time freelance photographer and has travelled extensively, including projects represented in this collection in Bosnia and Herzegovina, the Caribbean, Central and South America, the Middle East, the Ukraine, and the border between Mexico and the Southwestern U.S. She has won many awards, especially for the Prix de la Photography de Paris, and has exhibited her work in galleries and institutions all over the world.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to educational, non-commercial use. Any other use requires express consent of the photographer.
Digital videos and digital images are open to use; they can be viewed only in the Rubenstein Library reading room.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Petra Barth photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchases in 2008, 2010, 2012, 2014, 2017, and 2018.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of 421 black-and-white prints, darkroom and digital, 726 associated digital image and project files, and two digital videos by photographer Petra Barth. Arranged by project, the photographs document the cultures, politics, environments, and crises in countries all over the world, and her interest in portraiture. Series include The Americas, whose images range from Central and South American countries to Caribbean countries of Haiti and the Bahamas; migrants and migrant services at the Arizona/Mexico border; the Chernobyl Exclusion Zone and residents in nearby areas in the Ukraine; scenes in Jerusalem and the West Bank; refugees in Jordan camps; and portraits of military veterans of the Bosnia-Herzegovina War, in the city of Sarajevo. In addition to many portraits of individuals and families, there are also landscapes.
Areas represented in The Americas series include Bolivia; Patagonia, Argentina; the Bahamas; Foz do Iguaçu and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil; El Salvador; Guatemala; Martissant, Cité Soleil, and Port-au-Prince, Haiti; Nicaragua; Ciudad del Este, Paraguay; and Cusco, Peru. Includes images of people working, cooking, minding children, participating in local festivals, traveling, and playing. Several portraits feature people in traditional dress. The largest group of images was taken in Haiti, where Barth returned following the 2010 earthquake. These photographs include scenes of people among the rubble in Martissant and Port-au-Prince, as well as some portraits of hospital patients. The Americas series images are arranged alphabetically by country.
The two short digital videos were taken by Barth in South America and the Chernobyl Exclusion Zone.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Related Materials
Petra Barth has published several photobooks based on her work: Mesoamerica (2007), from her work in Central and South America; and Los Mochileros / The Backpackers (2016), part of her U.S./Mexico border crossing documentary work. Both titles are held by Rubenstein Library.
Border stations -- Arizona -- Photographs; Carnival -- Bolivia -- Oruro -- Photographs; Chernobyl Nuclear Accident, Chornobylʹ, Ukraine, 1986; Documentary films -- United States; Documentary photography; Haiti Earthquake, Haiti, 2010 -- Social aspects; Human Rights -- Mexico; Immigrants -- Mexico -- Portraits; Portrait photography; Refugee camps -- Jordan -- Photographs; Refugees -- Portraits; Veterans -- Bosnia and Herzegovina -- Portraits; Arizona -- Boundaries -- Photographs; Bahamas -- Photographs; Bogotá (Colombia) -- Photographs; Bolivia -- Photographs; Chernobyl -- Photographs; Ciudad del Este (Paraguay) -- Photographs; Concepcíon (Chile) -- Photographs; Cuzco (Peru) -- Photographs; El Salvador -- Photographs; Foz do Iguaçu (Brazil) -- Photographs; Guatemala -- Photographs; Haiti -- Photographs; Jerusalem -- Photographs; Jordan -- Photographs; Mexico -- Boundaries -- United States -- Photographs; Nicaragua -- Photographs; Patagonia (Argentina and Chile) -- Photographs; Rio de Janeiro (Brazil) -- Photographs; Sarajevo (Bosnia and Herzegovina) -- Photographs; Ukraine -- Photographs; West Bank -- Photographs; Audiovisual materials; Black-and-white photographs; Digital moving image formats; Digital prints; Gelatin silver prints; Inkjet prints; Video recordings; Barth, Petra; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- The Americas (Central America, South America, and Caribbean), 2006-2020; 2006-ongoing
  Scope and Contents note
  Series comprises 99 traditional darkroom black-and-white photographs, 127 digital image files, and one digital video (2 mins., 18 secs.) documenting life and culture, and landscapes in the Caribbean, Central America, and South America, with a focus on Bolivia.
  Digital image files are associated with the Bolivia series, and include TIFs, PSDs, and a PDF contact sheet.
  The photographic prints are arranged in series chiefly by country and then by travel dates; they measure approximately 16x20 inches. Areas represented are Patagonia and Argentina; the Bahamas; the Altiplano region of Bolivia; Foz do Iguaçu and Rio de Janeiro, Brazil; El Salvador; Guatemala; Martissant, Cité Soleil, and Port-au-Prince, Haiti; Nicaragua; Ciudad del Este, Paraguay; and Cusco, Peru.
  Images show people working and farming, cooking, minding children, socializing, parading, traveling, going to market, resting, and playing games. Several portraits feature people in traditional dress.
  The largest groups of images are from Bolivia, El Salvador, and Haiti. The Haiti photographs, taken when Barth returned following the 2010 earthquake, include scenes of destroyed buildings, street life, and people among the rubble in the epicenter zone, at Martissant, and in the capital, Port-au-Prince.
  The digital video (2 mins., 18 secs.) chiefly shows landscapes in Nicaragua and Honduras, most shot from a moving vehicle, border crossings, and possibly other South American locations.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server; digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room.
  - Argentina (Patagonia), 2010 April; 3 prints
    - Patagonia, finished prints, 3 prints (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bahamas, 2010 April, August; 3 prints
    - Bahamas, finished prints, 3 prints (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bolivia, 2009-2010; 42 prints; 122 digital files
    - El Alto, La Paz, finished prints, 2010 February; 1 prints (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Uyuni, finished prints, 2010 July; 1 prints (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Oruro, Carnaval; El Alto; Altiplano; La Paz, finished prints, 2009; 25 prints; 5 folders (Box 4)
      Scope and Contents
      The Carnaval celebration in Oruro is designated by UNESCO as a heritage site. Prints measure 13x19 inches.
    - Oruro, Carnaval; El Alto; Altiplano; La Paz, finished prints, 2009; 15 prints; 3 folders (Box 5)
      The Carnaval celebration in Oruro is designated by UNESCO as a heritage site. Prints measure 17x22 inches.
    - Bolivia, TIF image files, 2009-2010; 40 files; 4.82 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0001)
    - Bolivia, PSD files, 2009-2010; 41 files; 7.44 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0001)
    - Bolivia, JPEG image files, 2009-2010; 40 files; 6.17 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0001)
    - Bolivia, contact sheet, 1 Adobe PDF file (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0001)
  - Brazil, 2008, 2010; 7 prints
    - Rio de Janeiro, finished prints, 2008 March; 2 prints (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Foz do Iguaçu, finished prints, 2010 April; 5 prints (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chile, Colombia, El Salvador, Guatemala, 2006, 2007, 2010; 6 prints
    - Concepcíon, Chile, finished prints, 2010 March; 1 prints (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bogotá, Colombia, finished prints, 2010 March; 2 prints (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Suchitoto, El Salvador, finished prints, 2007 March; 1 prints (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - San Antonio Palopó, Guatemala, finished prints, 2006 July; 1 prints (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Huehuetenango, Guatemala, finished prints, 2006 July; 1 prints (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - El Salvador, 2007; 49 prints
    - El Salvador, finished prints, 49 prints 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Haiti, 2009-2010; 20 prints
    Large series of images was taken in Haiti, where Barth returned following the devastating 2010 earthquake, centered about 16 miles west of the capital of Port-au-Prince. Photographs include scenes of people among the rubble in Martissant and Port-au-Prince, and portraits of people of all ages, including some of hospital patients.
    - Martissant, Haiti, finished prints, 2009 October; 8 prints (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Martissant, Haiti, finished prints, 2009 October; 3 prints (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Martissant, Haiti, finished prints, 2010 March; 4 prints (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Cité Soleil, Haiti, finished prints, 2010 March; 2 prints (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Port-au-Prince, Haiti, finished prints, 2010 March; 2 prints (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Martissant, Haiti, finished prints, 2010 March; 1 prints (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Nicaragua, 2006; 4 prints
    - Matagalpa, Nicaragua, 2006 July; 3 prints (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Managua, Nicaragua, 2006 October; 1 prints (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Paraguay and Peru, 2010; 5 prints
    - Ciudad del Este, Paraguay, 2010 April; 2 prints (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Cusco, Peru, 2010 July; 3 prints (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - On Location in South America video, mp4 file, 2012 April 24; 1 mp4 file; 35.9 MB
    The digital video can only be accessed in the Rubenstein Library reading room.
    Digital video (2 mins., 18 secs.) shows footage of mountains, rainforests, a coastline, a large lake, street life, border crossings, what appear to be small mining operations, and other scenes, shot in Nicaragu and the Honduras, and possibly other South American locations. Much of the footage was shot from a moving vehicle. The soundtrack consists of acoustic indigenous music.
    - MPEG-4 master (Video-file RL10024-MP4-0002)
      Digital file can only be accessed in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room.
  - Petra Barth website, 2014-2020; 2014-ongoing
- Arizona/Mexico Border, circa 2013-2016
  Series consists of two subgroups, each representing a different project by photographer Petra Barth, exploring the natural and built environment as well as the human stories of the border crossing between Arizona and Mexico. Each series comprises photographic prints as well as associated electronic files.
  The 57 black-and-white digitally printed photographs in the first subseries document border crossings, desert locations, and various services and shelters supported by the Comedor/Kino Border, ARSOBO/ArizonaSonoraBorder, and San Juan Bosco Albergue Para Immigrantes initiatives, in partnership with: BCA Border Community Alliance, FESAC Fondacioa Del Empresariado Sonorese, A.C. The prints measure 13x19 inches. Associated digital records include image files and one contact sheet.
  The second subseries, entitled "Los Mochileros," or "The Backpackers," embodies 32 stark portraits of migrants, mostly men but also a few women, who are awaiting deportation decisions on the border between Arizona and Nogales. The prints measure 13x19 inches and are digitally printed. Associated digital records include book layouts as well as image files and Barth's statement's about the project.
  - Arizona/Mexico Border, 2013; 57 prints, 115 digital files
    This project comprises portraits of migrants as well as landscapes and buildings at the border crossing between Arizona and Mexico. The digital inkjet prints measure 13x19 inches. Associated digital image files are included.
    - Arizona/Mexico, finished prints, 57 prints (Box 8)
    - Arizona/Mexico, PSD image files, 58 files; 6.08 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0002)
    - Arizona/Mexico, DNG image files, 55 files; 1.86 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0002)
    - Arizona/Mexico, digital contact sheets, 2 .pdf files; 11.0 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0002)
  - The Backpackers / Los Mochileros, circa 2013-2016; 32 prints; 66 digital files
    These 32 untitled 13x19 inch black-and-white inkjet photographic prints record the faces of the migrants who await their fates at the border of the United States and Mexico. The portraits are anonymous, are mostly of men, though there are also several women, and were taken at the San Juan Bosco shelter for deportees.
    In addition to the prints and the associated digital image files, there is the photographer's statement about the Backpackers project, and several digital book layout and book block files related to publications, one of which contains an essay on the border wall.
    - The Backpackers / Los Mochileros, finished prints (Box 9)
    - The Backpackers, PSD image files, 31 files; 7.80 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0002)
    - The Backpackers, JPEG image files, 31 files; 227 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0002)
    - The Backpackers, other digital materials, 4 files (3 .pdf, 1 Word .doc); 74.5 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0002)
      Four electronic files include a 2016 digital maquette of the book block (all interior pages), a layout for the 2017 Bienniale in Venice exhibit publication, one contact sheet, and the photographer's project statement.
- Chernobyl, Ukraine, 2009-2012; 92 prints; 129 digital files
  The 92 black-and-white digital inkjet prints, digital video (2 mins., 19 secs.), and associated digital image files in this series document various sites surrounding the Chernobyl nuclear power plant in what is now Ukraine, abandoned after a catastrophic breach in April 1986. The prints measure 13x19 and 17x22 inches.
  Locations include abandoned cities and towns (Pripyat is one of the most well-known) and other sites in the exclusion zone; inhabited villages and towns outside the exclusion zone; and the exclusion zone visitors center. Included are many portraits of resettled refugees; squatters; and visitors to the areas.
  The digital video records landscapes, abandoned buildings and other locations, and official escorts with Geiger counters.
  - Chernobyl, finished prints, 25 prints 5 folders 13x19 inches (Box 4)
  - Chernobyl, finished prints, 32 prints 7 folders 13x19 inches (Box 6)
  - Chernobyl, finished prints, 35 prints 7 folders 17x22 inches (Box 7)
  - Exclusion Zone Chernobyl video, mp4 file, 2012 May 17; 138 Megabytes 1 mp4 file 2 minutes, 19 seconds (Video-file RL10024-MP4-0001)
    Video footage features landscapes, abandoned buildings and other locations, and official escorts with Geiger counters.
  - Chernobyl, TIF image files, 35 files; 3.77 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0003)
  - Chernobyl, PSD image files, 92; 13.6 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0003)
  - Chernobyl, digital contact sheet (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0003)
    1 .pdf; 28.5 MB
- Market of the Heroes, Sarajevo, 2017 July; 54 prints; 188 digital files
  Series consists of 54 black-and-white inkjet prints, measuring 13x19 inches, along with associated digital files. The majority of the images are individual and group portraits of veterans of the war in Bosnia and Herzegovina, gathered in a Sarajevo city square in summer of 2017. There are also photographs of panoramic city views, street views, Jewish cemeteries, monuments, and buildings with bullet holes.
  In addition to image files in various formats, the digital components include a Word document containing the photographer's statement about the project, as well as three pages of short biographies of each individual whose portraits are in the collection. A hard copy of this document accompanies the photographs in the box.
  - Market of the Heroes, finished prints, 10 prints 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Market of the Heroes, finished prints, 54 prints 11 folders (Box 10)
  - TIF image files, 56 files; 7.30 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0004)
  - JPEG image files, 57 files; 390 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0004)
  - Supporting material files, 2 files (Word .doc, .pdf); 15.7 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0004)
- Jerusalem / West Bank / Jordan, 2016-2017; 6 folders 1 box 47 prints; 101 digital files
  The 16 black-and-white digital photographs featuring the city of Jerusalem and the West Bank have as their focus buildings, streets, and inhabitants. The prints measure 13x19 inches.
  The 31 black-and-white digital prints in Jordan were taken by Barth in refugee camps housing thousands of displaced people, mainly from Syria, but also from Iraq and Palestine. Portraits include men, women, children, and family groups, in their temporary housing and at refugee processing centers. The prints measure 13x19 inches.
  The photographic prints in this series are accompanied by digital images files and the photographer's statement about displaced peoples, the refugee camps, and her project to document life there.
  - Jerusalem / West Bank, finished prints, 2016-2017; 16 prints 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Displaced (Refugees in Jordan), finished prints, 2016; 31 prints 4 folders (Box 11)
  - PSD image files, 47 files; 10.1 GB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0005)
  - JPEG image files, 47 files; 564 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0005)
  - Supporting material files, 13 files (12 .pdfs, 1 Word .doc); 154 MB (Digital-materials RL10024-SET-0005)